Guide to the Sir George Hubert Wilkins Papers
The Ohio State University. Byrd Polar and Climate Research Center Archival Program.
- Series XVII: Artifacts, 1883-1956
  - Army Photo Pin, undated (Box 42, Folder 14)
    This U.S. Army pin features a photo of Wilkins with caption "Q4 SIR HUBERT WILKINS". It appears to have been broken and glued together.
  - Japanese Fans from the Graf Zeppelin Trip, 1928 (Box 42, Folder 15-16)
  - Silverware from the submarine Nautilus, 1931 (Box 42, Folder 17)
    Enclosed in a dark colored case with velvet lining is silverware from the submarine Nautilus. This silverware bears an N in the pattern. In 1931, Sir Wilkins commanded the Nautilus on an Arctic expedition under the ice. In the case are three sets of silverware.
    Box 42 item 19 contains an additional two sets of Nautilus silverware.
  - Medallion from Sociedad Geografica de Cuba, 1914 (Box 42, Folder 18)
    This medal was given by the Sociedad Geografica de Cuba in 1914 to Sir George Hubert Wilkins. The front reads (in Latin): "DA OPERAM QUO SPLENDIDA INSULA QUAM HABITAMUS MAGIS AC MAGIS DIGNOSCATUR". The medallion is enclosed in a large case that reads: "Sir George Hubert Wilkins Gran Medalla de Oro MCMXXVIII de la Sociedad Geografica de Cuba"
  - Silverware from the submarine Nautilus (2 sets), 1931 (Box 42, Folder 19)
    see also Box 42 item 17, which is Nautilus silverware in case.
  - Opera Glasses, undated (Box 42, Folder 21)
    These opera glasses belonged to Suzanne Wilkins and consist of two separate piece - the binoculars and the handle.
  - Passport, 1919-1923 (Box 42, Folder 22)
    This passport was issued January 17, 1919, to Sir George Hubert Wilkins. Included is his occupation, physical description, photo, signature, and several stamps that indicate where and when Wilkins traveled post-WWI. Endorsements include: Italy, New Zealand, France, Chile, the United States, Argentina, Uruguay, and Switzerland.
  - New South Wales Motor Traffic Act and Regulations Envelope Cover, undated (Box 42, Folder 23)
    Now empty, this thick cardboard envelope cover may have enclosed a driver's license or manual.
  - Guaranty Trust Company of New York Billfold, ca. 1940s (Box 42, Folder 24)
    This billfold bears the Guaranty Trust Co. monogram on the front, a bank that eventually became JPMorgan Chase. On the inside, it reads Guaranty Trust Co. and its affiliated cities. This billfold (or possibly checkbook) was in an envelope with a description of the item written by Wilkins' secretary Winston Ross. It reads: "Sir HW's Guaranty Trust Billfold- Carried through France etc. 1940 and when shot down while escaping with two French Generals who had "absconded" with silver, jewels, etc."
  - Cine-Kodak Filter Outfit for F-1-9 Cine-Kodak Models B & BB, undated; box includes 4 filters (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - Stereotanex Camera in Case, 1912 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    Case encloses a Goerz camera, a Kodak film pack, and an empty film cartridge. The camera is Stereotanex camera, manufactured by CP Goerz in Berlin. It is missing some pieces, including one of the lenses. The camera is dated 1912, which is the same year Wilkins was sent by the Gaumont Company of London to photograph the Balkan War. Also included in this case is a Kodak film pack with 12 exposures and an empty, black film cartridge.
  - Camera, undated (Box 43, Folder 16)
  - Two St. Clement Hofbauer medallions, undated; .75 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - 1/2 Mark German Bank Note: 1944 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Envelope containing part of Carl Shrewsbury's motor tube that traveled more than 103 3/4 miles in 10 minutes continuous run, driven by Percy Lambert, England, 1913 (sic 1912) (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Envelope addressed to Wilkins in NY: 1931. Contains pamphlet on "The Seventh Tract" - St. Benedict's medal, small envelope containing small metal screw (wood) (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Envelope containing a small penguin feather, sent to WR (Winston Ross) by HW (Hubert Wilkins), undated (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - One Baht note from Thailand with explanation of significance, 1958 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Envelope contains "All that's left of SW (Suzanne Wilkins) _ $1000 Indian Rug....", undated (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - ID card: Letter of Indication for the Canadian Bank of Commerce- Travlers' Cheques, 1916 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Extreme Cold Weather Mask, ca. 1940s (Box 46, Folder 1)
    This is an extreme cold weather mask that may have been a prototype for the US Army. In 1942 Wilkins became a consultant for the US Army on extreme weather clothing and survival techniques. This mask fabric may be a precursor to modern polyurethane or foam rubber. The mask features holes over the nose and mouth area to allow easier breathing and wire-caged eye holes, possibly to prevent fogging.
  - Aviator Goggles with Case, undated (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Cover, Protective, individual, Cold Climate, ca. 1940s (Box 46, Folder 3)
    This item is compressed, single-use body bag that when released, is large enough to protect and entire person, weapon, and equipment. The original 1944 design of this "cape" was to cover an individual from sprayed vesicants. Later, a 1945 model also protected against blistering gases. This specific item seems to be a prototype designed to be effective in cold weather climates. In 1942, Wilkins became a consultant for the US Military on extreme weather clothing and survival techniques, so this item may have been designed under his advisement. The stock number on this item reads 72-C-1100 as opposed to the traditional 1945 model which is stock no. 72-C-1000. Contract no. is W 36-030 QM-608. On the back, it reads: "This cover is to protect YOU against sprayed blister gasses. When ready to open pull here." This containing wrap has been partially opened, but the item itself has not been opened. Though these covers were part of the gas mask kit and intended for the biological/chemical warfare purposes, more often these covers were used in case of rain or for need of shelter, giving a more emergency blanket purpose, which makes this cold climate version even more important. There is no evidence that this cold weather cover was mass produced or issued.
  - World War II Emergency Signaling Mirror - ESM/2, ca. 1940s (Box 46, Folder 4)
    This is an Emergency Signaling Mirror from the World War II period. The original ESM/1 is dated 1943 and this model, the ESM/2, came shortly after. The survival mirror was manufactured by General Electric and has a wax paper cover. The back mirror part has developed some black spots with age. Sir George Hubert Wilkins began a consulting position with the United States Army in 1942 in the departments of extreme cold and hot clothing and survival techniques.
  - Emergency Signaling Mirror - M580A, 1944 (Box 46, Folder 5)
    This emergency signaling mirror, specification M-508A, is also known as the reflex button type and utilized retroreflective materials rather than tempered gases. It was more accurate than its cross-hair predecessor such as the ESM/2. It began being issued in 1944 and is comprised of two tin halves. Through some models have the US Navy stamp on the tin, this specific mirror does not. This mirror also has the two tin halves taped together at one side so it opens without being separated. This model of mirror was not manufactured by General Electric. Instead, the manufacture is printed as "Signal Service Corporation, Irvington 11, New Jersey."
  - Goggles - 2 pairs, undated (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - World War II Extreme Heat Thermometer, ca. 1940s (Box 46, Folder 7)
    This mercury and glass thermometer was used in hot weather field tests in Arizona by Sir George Hubert Wilkins who was part of a group of U.S. Army climate specialists in the Research and Development Branch of the Quartermaster Corps during his years serving as a consultant for the military.
  - Tinplate pitcher and cups from Quest RYS, 1921 (Box 46, Folder 8-9)
    This is a tinplate, enamel pitcher and two cups from the Quest RYS, the vessel used for the Shackleton-Rowett Expedition of 1921-1922, Ernest Shackleton's last expedition. Shackleton was a member of the Royal Yacht Squadron and the Quest bore the RYS suffix. Sir George Hubert Wilkins participated in this expedition as chief of the scientific staff and naturalist. The pitcher and cups are "Goat brand" tinplate made by the Welsh Tinplate and Metal Stamping Company of Llanelli in South Wales.
  - World War I Army First Aid Kit and pouch, 1916 (Box 46, Folder 10)
    This painted brass First Aid Kit comes in a canvass pouch that may have been attached to a utility belt. The pouch has two buttons and is stamped "P.B. & Co. 1917." The tin itself is stamped: "FIRST AID PACKET- U.S. ARMY CONTRACT NOV. 2-1916. BAUER & BLACK CHICAGO, U.S.A. TO OPEN- PULL RING PATENT APPLIED FOR." In 1917, Wilkins was in France photographing the Australian Forces during World War I.
  - Concise Circular Slide Rule in Japanese, undated (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Eastern Airlines Decal Stickers, undated (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Fabric from Airship "Norge", 1926 (Box 46, Folder 13)
    This piece of fabric is from the airship "Norge" and is signed by the crew members on that expedition. The "Norge" was led by Roald Amudsen and flew over the North Pole just days after Admiral Richard E. Byrd in May, 1926. The back reads: From the airship "Norge" Svalbard- Alaska 11/5- 14/5 1926. It is signed by Birger Gottwald, Hjalmar Risser-Larsen, Emil Horgen, Frithjof Storm-Johnsen, and Fredrik Ramm. At the bottom is says: To Captain Wilkins
  - U.S. Army Quartermaster Corp Patches, undated (Box 46, Folder 15)
  - Philatelic and general rubber stamps, various (Box 46, Folder 16)
    View Image In the Wilkins collection, there are 38 rubber stamps. Most of these were used for philatelic mail during the 1931 Nautilus expedition. The addresses on the cover were used twice- both as the sender and the receiver- resulting in dual franking on the covers. The rubber in the collection include the To: and From: stamps that were used to kill the original to/from marks. Also included in this box are the routing stamps that show the place of origination and destination for each cover, i.e. "New York to North Pole." Other stamps include the three different cachet stamps used (one with the year, one without the year, and one without any words), an Air Mail stamp, a Registered stamp, and a Wilkins return address stamp. For complete listing of stamps, please
  - Penguin feathers, including down, tail feather, back and white feathers, undated (Box 47, Folder 1-4)
    View image
  - Vegetation specimens, 1950-1951 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    This notebook is full of vegetation specimens showing typical edge of forest color in vicinity of Churchill Manitoba, 1950-1951. The accuracy of color may no longer be accurate due to age.
  - Rock specimens, undated (Box 47, Folder 6)
    This is a set of nine rocks. An attached tag indicates that they came from the Mineral Department of the British Museum.
  - Cloth Pattern, undated (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Fur lined leather boots, undated (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Model of Nautilus, SSN 571, green/gray, 1958 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Model of Nautilus, SSN 571 (black), 1958 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Rubber Stamp - Antarctica North Pole-South Pole, Sep.12 - Oct.17, 1957. (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Tin Matchbox, undated (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Polaroid All Purpose Goggle Kit no. 1019, ca. 1940s (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Experimental Ground Anchor with guy wire assembly, undated (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Carved Boomerang, 1938 (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - swatches of white fabric, undated (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Yellow signal flag carried by Ellsworth on Polar Star across Antarctica, undated (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Inflatable plastic British Flag, July 3, 1928 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Black and White diagonal flag, undated (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Thermos from submarine Nautilus, 1931 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Jupiter Rex Certificate, 1932 (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Moccasins (child's), undated (Box 49, Folder 14)
    View Image Inuit shoes (eskimo)? No accompanying documentation, though they are small, perhaps belonging to a child.
  - Typewriter, Undated (Box 50, Folder 0)
  - Radio Receiver, Undated (Box 51, Folder 0)
  - Parts to chernikeeff log, Undated (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Thorens Excelda Portable Record Player, ca 1930 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Kodak Eastman Folding Pocket Camera, ca 1900 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - USA Yacht Ensign, Undated (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - American Optical "Super Vent" all rubber goggle, ca 1945 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Polaroid All Purpose Goggle Kit, 1021A (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Goggles with metal lens, Undated (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - Pin from Graf Zepplin Around The World Flight, Undated (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Kodak Signet 35 Camera, 1951-1958 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Cline Kodak Model BB Video Camera, 1925-1930 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Russian Search Diary, 1937 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - 6 oz Bovril Pemmican food can, Undated (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Eskimo Arts and Crafts film reel, 1947 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Ski Pole, Undated (Box OV-28, Folder 0)
  - Typewriter, Undated (Box OV-29, Folder 0)
  - 1 fur coat and 1 green army jacket, Undated (Box OV-30, Folder 0)
  - 1 pair of pants and 1 green army jacket, Undated (Box OV-31, Folder 0)
  - 1 fur coat and 1 green army coat, Undated (Box OV-32, Folder 0)
  - 1 pair of pants, 2 pairs of boots, and 1 hat, Undated (Box OV-33, Folder 0)
  - drawing by Clayton Knight: Wilkins and Lockheed Vega 1926-1928 Arctic Expedition, Undated (Box OV-34, Folder 0)
  - oil painting by Suzanne Wilkins: Wilkins and Eilsen in front of the Lockheed Vega after flying from Point Barrow to Spitzbergen, April 1928, Undated (Box OV-35, Folder 0)
  - oil painting by Fred Myers, Lockheed over Arctic, July 9, 1928, Undated (Box OV-36, Folder 0)